Maria Edgeworth Papers,1799-1852 C1664
Manuscripts Division
Maria Edgeworth Papers
1799-1852
Manuscripts Division
Edgeworth, Maria, 1768-1849
C1664
2.0 linear feet
4 boxes
Consists primarily of Maria Edgeworth's notebooks and sketchbooks for various literary projects. There is also correspondence between Edgeworth and others, including letters to various publishers concerning the printing of her work, as well as a small amount of miscellaneous material including rent slips, a copy of her poem "Jacob," a copy of a will of a publisher at Baldwin & Craddock, an advertisement for an octavo edition of her work, and a leather carrying case.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from The Cotswold Auction Company in 2020 (AM 2021-30).
Appraisal
No materials were removed from the collection during 2021 processing beyond routine appraisal practices.
Arrangement
As no original order was discernible, materials were arranged by type/genre.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of literary sketchbooks and notebooks used by Maria Edgeworth, many of which she titled. There is also correspondence between Edgeworth and several others regarding her work, including literary publishers Richard Bentley and R. Hunter, as well as other miscellanous materials such as rent slips, a copy of her poem "Jacob," a copy of a will, an advertisement for an octavo edition, and a small leather carrying case.
Edgeworth
Biographical / Historical
Maria Edgeworth was an Anglo-Irish author of adults' and children's literature. Born in Oxfordshire, Maria spent most of her childhood in England. After her mother, Anna Maria Edgeworth (née Elers)'s death, she went to live with her father, Richard Lovell Edgeworth, at his estate in County Longford, Ireland. The time she spent in Ireland was impactful, and this was reflected in her writing celebrating Irish culture and its rejection of English steretypes of Ireland. She is considered one of the first realists in children's literature, and her writing played a significant role in the evolution of the novel in Europe at the time. She also wrote about her views on various topics including economis, politics, estate management, and education, and was well regarded in English literary society. She died in 1849 at Edgeworthstown in Ireland.
Authors, Irish -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Novelists, Irish -- 19th century -- Sources.; Irish literature; Women novelists, Irish; Authors, English -- 19th century.; Letters.; Notebooks.
- Notebooks and Sketchbooks, 1799-1849; 7 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-4, Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes notebooks/sketchbooks for various literary projects. Edgeworth titled most of the notebooks, which are as follows: "Sketches for The Paren'ts Assistant and Popular Tales"; "Madam de Fleury and English Misanthrope; Modern Sketches"; "Sketches for Popular Tales and Orphans"; "Lenora"; "Nora"; "Ennui"; "Rosanna"; "Harry Owen or The Snow Woman"; "Miscellaneous Irish"; "Sketch of the Freeman Family"; "Out of Debt, Out of Danger, and Murad the Unlucky"; "Absentee"; "Manouvring and Vivian"; "Hints for Harry and Lucy"; "Pleasure's Price"; "Parent's Assistant; Basket Woman; Waste Not, Want Not"; "Take for Granted"; "Notes and Emile de Coulanges or Great and Little Sacrifices"; "Orlandini"; "Angelina or My Bosom[?] Friend"; "The Captain or Eton Montem"; "The Conract and the Will; The Blessing and the Curse; The Genesis or the Adventurer; By and By"; "Whim for Whim or Something New, Something Old; Little Merchants"; "Forrester or the Adventurer"; "Unfashionable Tales"; "Sketches for Moral Tales; Abroad and at Home; Belinda"; "All for Effect or The Irish [Heights?]"; "Literary Projects Written 1849"
- Correspondence, 1804-1852; 7 folders
  Contains correspondence between Maria Edgeworth and several others including publishers Richard Bentley, R. Hunter, and Baldwin and Craddock. There is also a letter to the wife of former Baldwin & Craddock publisher Mr. Joseph Johnston.
  - Bentley, Richard, 1834-1852; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes original correspondence and copies of letters between Maria Edgeworth and literary publisher Richard Bentley often pertaining to the printing of Edgeworth's work.
  - Hunter, R., 1816-1817; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Johnson, Joseph, 1804 May 30; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lockhart, J.S., 1852; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Murray, John, 1815; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Maria Edgeworth, 1821-1835; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Contains letters and copies of letters from Maria Edgeworth to various correspondents.
  - Letters to Maria Edgeworth, 1825-1847; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Letters and fragments written to Maria Edgeworth from various correspondents.
- Advertisement to the Octavo Edition, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Rent Slips, 1849; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Rent slips likely addressed to Maria Edgeworth's stepmother.
- Copy of "Jacob", undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Copy of the Will of Joseph Johnson, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
  publisher previous to R. Hunter in Baldwin & Craddock,
- Brown Leather Carrying Case, undated; 1 box (Box 4)